<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

<book>
    <bookinfo>
        <title>JTrac</title>
        <subtitle>JTrac Reference Documentation</subtitle>
        <releaseinfo>2.0-EA1</releaseinfo>
        <authorgroup>
            <author>
                <firstname>Peter</firstname>
                <surname>Thomas</surname>
            </author>
        </authorgroup>
    </bookinfo>

    <toc/>

    <preface id="preface">
        <title>Preface</title>

        <para>
            This document is a reference guide for <ulink url="http://jtrac.info">JTrac</ulink>
            - the generic issue tracking web-application.  This document is not only a user-guide
            but also useful as a reference for developers interested in contributing to JTrac or extending it.
        </para>

        <para>
            This documentation has been generated using the DocBook configuration 
            used by the <ulink url="http://www.springframework.org">Spring Framework</ulink> development team. 
            This particular simplified DocBook helper package was originally developed by Chris Bauer of the
            <ulink url="http://www.hibernate.org">Hibernate</ulink> project.  Thanks go out to all those who
            perfected this very handy approach.
        </para>
    </preface>

    <chapter id="introduction">
        <title>Introduction</title>

        <sect1 id="introduction-about">
            <title>About</title>
            <para>
                JTrac is a generic issue-tracking web-application that can be easily customized by adding 
                custom fields and drop-downs. Features include customizable workflow, field level permissions, 
                e-mail integration, file attachments and a detailed history view.
            </para>                        
        </sect1>        
        
        <sect1 id="introduction-features">
            <title>Features</title>
            <sect2 id="introduction-features-customfields">
                <title>Custom Fields</title>
                <para>
                    You can easily add the following types of custom fields to a tracker project.
                    JTrac can be used to effectively track various kinds of things such as Bugs, Action Items and Tasks.
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Drop Down List</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Free Text Field</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Date Picker</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>(Decimal) Number</para>
                        </listitem>                                
                    </itemizedlist>
                <para>
                    A future version of JTrac will support "nested" items under a first-level "parent" item.
                    This will allow users to split tasks into sub-tasks.  This also opens up possibilities for 
                    JTrac to become a requirements capture tool or a general-purpose review record
                    tool or even a test-case management tool.
                </para>                    
                </para>
            </sect2>
            <sect2 id="introduction-features-customworkflow">
                <title>Custom Workflow</title>
                <para>
                    Each tracker project that you create can have a different workflow.  JTrac allows for 
                    complete customization of the tracker-item lifecycle, right down to the names of
                    each intermediate state.  You can even configure whether or not field value editing is
                    permitted for each state - and that too at a field-level.
                </para>
            </sect2>
            <sect2 id="introduction-features-customroles">
                <title>Custom Roles</title>
                <para>
                    JTrac customization does not stop at workflow - you can also define different roles for each tracker
                    project that you set up.  This allows for tremendous flexibility - for example you could define that
                    a "DEVELOPER" role can only mark "Assigned" items as "Fixed" and that only a "TESTER" role has the
                    power to mark a "Fixed" item as "Closed".  JTrac allows you complete control over the workflow and
                    you can easily tweak it to fit your existing process rather than the other way around.
                </para>
                <para>
                    Also, field-level permissions can be mapped to roles.  This allows for even more flexibility - for
                    example, you can set a project up so that only a "MANAGER" can change the "Severity" level after a
                    bug is submitted.
                </para>
                <para>
                    In a future version of JTrac, the ability to even hide fields depending on the role and status
                    will be implemented.  The design for this is already in place.
                </para>                  
            </sect2>             
        </sect1>

        <sect1 id="introduction-overview">
            <title>Overview</title>

            <para>para1</para>

            <para>para2</para>

            <para>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject role="html">
                        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/test.gif" format="GIF"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>Figure 1: Caption</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </para>

            <sect2 id="introduction-why">
                <title>Why</title>

                <para>para1</para>

                <para>para2</para>
            </sect2>
        </sect1>
    
    </chapter>
</book>