<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

<book>
    <bookinfo>
        <title>JTrac</title>
        <subtitle>User / Developer Guide</subtitle>
        <releaseinfo>2.0 [final]</releaseinfo>
        <authorgroup>
            <author>
                <firstname>Peter</firstname>
                <surname>Thomas</surname>
            </author>
        </authorgroup>
    </bookinfo>

    <toc/>

    <preface id="preface">
        <title>Preface</title>
        <para>
            This document is a reference guide for <ulink url="http://jtrac.info">JTrac</ulink>
            - the generic issue tracking web-application.  This document is not only a user-guide
            but can also serve as a reference for developers interested in contributing to JTrac.
        </para>
        <para>
            This documentation has been generated using the DocBook configuration 
            used by the <ulink url="http://www.springframework.org">Spring</ulink> development team. 
            This particular simplified DocBook helper package was originally developed by Chris Bauer of the
            <ulink url="http://www.hibernate.org">Hibernate</ulink> project.  Thanks go out to all those who
            perfected this very handy approach.
        </para>
    </preface>

    <chapter id="introduction">
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <sect1 id="introduction-about">
            <title>About</title>
            <para>
                JTrac is a generic issue-tracking web-application that can be easily customized by adding 
                custom fields and drop-downs. Features include customizable workflow, field level permissions, 
                e-mail integration, file attachments and a detailed history view.
            </para>
            <para>
                JTrac was created after the author felt that he could write a much better alternative to a 
                commercial defect tracking tool that he was having to use. Development started in 2004. 
                JTrac is ideal for issue tracking but is so generic that you can use it to track well - almost anything.
            </para>
            <para>
                JTrac development used to be hosted at <ulink url="https://jtrac.dev.java.net"/> but moved to SourceForge 
                in early 2006. The older working version was based on Spring JDBC and MS Access and is not being maintained
                any more.  JTrac was completely re-written to use <ulink url="http://www.hibernate.org/">Hibernate</ulink>
                for persistence and the <ulink url="http://www.acegisecurity.org/">Acegi Security</ulink> framework for Spring 
                and it now uses the latest Java 5.0 and JSP 2.0 features. 
            </para>            
        </sect1>        
        
        <sect1 id="introduction-releasenotes">
            <title>Release Notes: Version 2.0 [final]</title>
            <para>
                Note that the database schema has changed since 2.0-RC3.  If you are using an earlier version of JTrac in production
                you have to upgrade your database schema as well as the bundled Jetty web server.  
                Instructions on how to upgrade are available in the "<link linkend="upgrading">upgrading</link>" section
                of this document.
            </para>
            <para>
                JTrac now has internationalization in place.  Please contribute a translation to your
                language of choice, this is very easy to do and you can find out how to do so in the
                "<link linkend="dev-translating">developer guide</link>" section of this document.
            </para>
            <para>
                You are encouraged to try out JTrac and communicate your feedback and interest in future versions
                to the JTrac development team.  Note that you can be up and running with just Java 5 as a prerequisite
                because JTrac comes bundled with a small-footprint web-application server called 
                <ulink url="http://jetty.mortbay.org/">Jetty</ulink>. Since an embedded database called 
                <ulink url="http://www.hsqldb.org/">HSQLDB</ulink> is used by default, JTrac is extremely easy to evaluate.
                Please refer the <link linkend="installation">installation</link> section of this documentation for 
                more details.  For example, you can drop the WAR file into a server of your choice and immediately 
                start using JTrac.                
            </para>
        </sect1>         
    </chapter>
    
    <chapter id="features">
        <title>Features</title>
        <para>                    
            JTrac has all the features you would expect from a standard issue-tracking application such as 
            support for file-attachments and e-mail integration.  JTrac offers powerful customization options,
            especially in the areas of workflow and field-level permissions and compares well to even
            commercial tools.
        </para>        
        <sect1 id="features-easytoinstall">
            <title>Easy to Install</title>
            <para>
                One of the useful features of JTrac is that it is distributed with an embedded web-application server 
                (<ulink url="http://jetty.mortbay.org/">Jetty</ulink>) that has a very small footprint.  
                If you have Java 5 installed you can be up and running after downloading and extracting JTrac - by 
                simply using the provided start and stop scripts.  JTrac scans its environment on startup and if a 
                configured database is not detected, <ulink url="http://www.hsqldb.org/">HSQLDB</ulink> is used by 
                default.
            </para>
            <para>
                If you already have a web-application server that you wish to use (such as 
                <ulink url="http://tomcat.apache.org/">Tomcat</ulink>), you can just drop in the WAR file 
                provided and sign on into the application straight-away.
            </para>
            <para>
                You can refer the <link linkend="installation">installation</link> section of this document for 
                more details.  JTrac uses <ulink url="http://www.hibernate.org">Hibernate</ulink> and so it can 
                use any database <ulink url="http://www.hibernate.org/80.html">supported by Hibernate.</ulink>
            </para>                
        </sect1>            
        <sect1 id="features-customfields">
            <title>Custom Fields</title>
            <para>                    
                JTrac can be used to effectively track various kinds of things such as Bugs, Action Items and Tasks.
                You can easily add the following types of custom fields to a tracker project:
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Drop Down List</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Free Text Field</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Date Picker</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>(Decimal) Number</para>
                    </listitem>                                
                </itemizedlist>                   
            </para>
            <para>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject role="html">
                        <imagedata align="center" fileref="../images/custom-fields.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>Setting up custom fields for a project</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </para>                
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="features-customworkflow">
            <title>Custom Workflow</title>
            <para>
                Each tracker project that you create can have a different workflow.  JTrac allows for 
                complete customization of the tracker-item lifecycle, right down to the names of
                each intermediate state.  It is possible to create very sophisticated workflows and a visual 
                "map" of the workflow being edited is displayed below the state-transition toggle-buttons 
                to make it easier to manage.
            </para>
            <para>
                The default workflow shown below is ideal if you simply want to track issues with just
                two states - Open and Closed.  However, with just a few mouse clicks, you can turn this into 
                a complex workflow involving multiple states.
            </para>            
            <para>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject role="html">
                        <imagedata align="center" fileref="../images/custom-workflow-before.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>Default workflow - before customization</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </para>
            <para>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject role="html">
                        <imagedata align="center" fileref="../images/custom-workflow-after.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>Example of a workflow - after customization</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </para>
            <para>
                You can even configure whether or not changing of values is permitted given the current state 
                within the workflow - and that too at a field-level.  This flexibility allows for some 
                interesting possibilities.  For example, assume that you want to maintain a "percentage complete" 
                field that can be updated at any time during the life-cycle of an item. The screenshot below 
                demonstrates how you can set up a drop down field called "% Complete":
            </para>
            <para>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject role="html">
                        <imagedata align="center" fileref="../images/percent-complete-field.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>Setting up of a drop down custom field called "% Complete"</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </para>
            <para>
                Then when customizing the roles and field-level permissions, all you need to do is specify that
                the "% Complete" field is editable even when the status is "Open".
            </para>
            <para>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject role="html">
                        <imagedata align="center" fileref="../images/percent-complete-roles.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>Making a custom field editable even after an item is newly created</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </para>
            <para>
                This results in the "% Complete" field being available for updating whenever anyone views an item
                with a status of "Open".
            </para>
            <para>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject role="html">
                        <imagedata align="center" fileref="../images/percent-complete-history.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>Example of a custom field that can be updated even when status is "Open"</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </para>            
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="features-customroles">
            <title>Custom Roles</title>
            <para>
                JTrac customization does not stop at workflow - you can also define different roles for each tracker
                project that you set up.  This allows for power and flexibility.  For example you could enforce that
                a "DEVELOPER" role can only mark "Assigned" items as "Fixed" and that only a "TESTER" role has the
                power to mark a "Fixed" item as "Closed".  You can even disallow selected roles from being able to 
                create new items.  JTrac gives you complete control over the workflow and you can easily tweak it 
                to fit your existing process rather than the other way around.
            </para>           
            <para>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject role="html">
                        <imagedata align="center" fileref="../images/custom-roles.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>Example of workflow where each role has clearly defined responsibilities.</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </para>            
            <para>              
                Field-level permissions can be mapped to roles which allows for even more flexibility. 
                For example, you can set a project up so that only a "MANAGER" can change the "Severity" level 
                after a bug is submitted.  JTrac makes it possible for you to define very complex workflows, complete 
                with both Status and Role dependent field-level permissions, and you can do all this within a 
                single admin screen.                  
            </para>                
        </sect1>        
        <sect1 id="features-search">
            <title>Search Custom Fields</title>
            <para>
                The intuitive search screen (shown below) allows for easy execution of common queries such as
                find all items "logged by" or "assigned to" a user (or users).  JTrac allows for filtering even
                on custom fields.
            </para>
            <para>
                You can navigate back to the search setup screen from the search results screen and have the
                search parameters still active.  This is useful when trying to tweak complex queries by 
                trial and error.
            </para>                
            <para>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject role="html">
                        <imagedata align="center" fileref="../images/search.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>The search screen - which allows filtering on custom fields</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </para>                
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="features-dashboard">
            <title>Dashboard</title>
            <para>
                The default view when you log into JTrac is a very handy dashboard view that provides the most 
                frequently used statistics at a glance. You can click on any of the numbers to immediately bring up 
                the search results view listing the items matched. For example, clicking on the count of items 
                "Logged By Me" would immediately display the list of items initiated by the currently logged in user.
            </para>
            <para>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject role="html">
                        <imagedata align="center" fileref="../images/dashboard.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>Statistics at a glance and search results available with just one click</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </para>
            <para>
                For each Space, you can also drill-down to a finer level of detail  by clicking on the right-arrow 
                'expand' icon.  This expands the dashboard rows so that you can see a break-up of item counts, not only by
                whether 'logged by me' / 'assigned to me' - but against the custom workflow states defined for 
                the Space as well.  Again, it is possible to directly navigate to the items by clicking on the dashboard numbers.
            </para>
            <para>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject role="html">
                        <imagedata align="center" fileref="../images/dashboard-expanded.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>Expanded statistics for a Space showing counts by workflow status</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </para>            
        </sect1>            
        <sect1 id="features-searchall">
            <title>Search Across All Projects</title>
            <para>
                In addition to be able to search within a single space (project) JTrac allows for searching across
                all (or a sub set of) projects that a user is mapped to.  For example, in the screenshot of the
                dashboard above, there are two projects.  The "SEARCH" link at the top of the page (as well as the "search"
                link on the "totals" row) would bring up the search wizard that can search across all (or a subset of)
                the spaces assigned to the currently logged in user.
            </para>                
        </sect1>       
        <sect1 id="features-textsearch">
            <title>Full Text Search</title>
            <para>
                The summary and even the detailed descriptions of items are indexed and can be searched.
                Note that if you are upgrading or migrating databases, you may need to "re-index" which
                is an option available to admin users.
            </para>
            <para>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject role="html">
                        <imagedata align="center" fileref="../images/full-text-search.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>Lucene powered full text search with wildcard support</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </para>                 
        </sect1>        
        <sect1 id="features-excel">
            <title>Export to Excel</title>
            <para>
                JTrac is able to export the results of any search (or all items in a Space) as an Excel Sheet.
                The link for this appears at the top right of the search results screen.
            </para>
            <para>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject role="html">
                        <imagedata align="center" fileref="../images/excel-link.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>Download search results as an excel sheet</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </para>                
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="features-attachments">
            <title>Attachments Support</title>
            <para>
                You can upload file attachments at the time of creating of an item or as many times
                as required after an item has been created.
            </para>                
        </sect1>            
        <sect1 id="features-history">
            <title>Detailed History View</title>
            <para>
                JTrac provides a very detailed history view that completely captures all comments or status
                changes for an item.
            </para>
            <para>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject role="html">
                        <imagedata align="center" fileref="../images/history.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>When viewing a single item, the history can be seen in detail</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </para>                  
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="features-navigation">
            <title>Simple Navigation</title>
            <para>
                Most users will use only five screens in JTrac: Dashboard, Create, View, Search and Results.
                Navigation has been designed with usability and simplicity in mind.
            </para>                 
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="features-related">
            <title>Cross Referencing of Items</title>
            <para>
                You can establish bi-directional links between items.  For example you can mark an item as
                being a "duplicate of" another item.  You can easily navigate to related items (and back) when 
                viewing any particular item.
            </para>
            <para>
                The option to add related items appears at the bottom of the screen when viewing an item 
                (after it is created).  The navigation is designed so that you have the option to execute a 
                search before selecting an item to cross-reference.
            </para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="features-guest">
            <title>Read-Only Access</title>
            <para>
                When setting up a Space you can define whether this space can be viewed by users without 
                having to log-in.
            </para>
            <para>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject role="html">
                        <imagedata align="center" fileref="../images/guest-allowed.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>Specify if read-only anonymous access is allowed per-space</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </para>                 
        </sect1>             
        <sect1 id="features-email">
            <title>E-mail Integration</title>
            <para>
                All status changes for an item will trigger e-mail notifications by default.
                You can choose to add multiple users into a "notify list" at the time of raising a new item
                or updating the history for an item.
            </para>
            <para>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject role="html">
                        <imagedata align="center" fileref="../images/notify-list.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>Add multiple users to a "notify list" while creating or updating an item</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </para>
            <para>
                The e-mail content is very nicely formatted HTML and is laid out in the same way as how the screen looks
                within JTrac when viewing an item.  Users do not need to get used to a different or possibly
                less pleasing format such as plain-text.
            </para>
            <para>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject role="html">
                        <imagedata align="center" fileref="../images/email-notification.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>Example of an e-mail sent by JTrac</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </para>
            <para>
                Admin users can configure the SMTP / e-mail server that JTrac should use in the "Manage Settings" page.
                This page can be accessed from the "OPTIONS" menu.  JTrac also can handle an e-mail server that requires
                authentication or even a secure connection over HTTPS.
            </para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="features-i18n">
            <title>Multi-Language Support</title>
            <para>
                JTrac has complete internationalization support and you can change the user interface language instantly 
                by editing your user-profile.  Adding a translation is very easy and does not require any
                Java  development expertise.  See <link linkend="dev-translating">this section</link> of the developer
                guide for more details and please consider contributing translations to the JTrac project.
            </para>
        </sect1>
    </chapter>
    
    <chapter id="installation">
        <title>Installation</title>
        <sect1 id="installation-prerequisites">
            <title>Prerequisites</title>
            <para>    
                All you require in order to start using JTrac is Java 5.  Only a JRE (Java Runtime Environment)
                is required and not the full-blown JDK (Java Development Kit).
            </para>
            <para>    
                You can download Java from <ulink url="http://www.java.com/download"/>.  Once you have Java installed
                you can verify that your system is ready to run JTrac by opening a command prompt and typing the
                following command:
            </para>
            <para>
                <programlisting>

java -version
                </programlisting>
            </para>
            <para>
                If the system responds with a java version that is 1.5 or greater, you are ready to download and run JTrac.
            </para>            
        </sect1>        
        <sect1 id="installation-quick">
            <title>Quick Installation</title>
            <para>                    
                Once you have Java you can start using JTrac right away because you do not need to configure a web-application 
                server or a database.  JTrac embeds both of these (<ulink url="http://jetty.mortbay.org/">Jetty</ulink> and 
                <ulink url="http://www.hsqldb.org/">HSQLDB</ulink>) to make it easy for you to evaluate JTrac.
            </para>                  
            <para>            
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            First, download the latest release from  
                            <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=162983&amp;package_id=184104">
                            the JTrac downloads area</ulink>                           
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Extract the zip file into a directory of your choice</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Double-click on "start.bat" to start JTrac.  (If you are not on Windows, see below.) 
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Point your web-browser to <ulink url="http://localhost/jtrac"/></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Sign on with the user name "admin" and password "admin"</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Start using JTrac</para>
                    </listitem>                                 
                </itemizedlist>                 
            </para>
            <para>
                Note that you can use the "stop.bat" script to stop the application.  If you are not on Windows, you may want 
                to rename the start and stop *.bat files to e.g. *.sh for Linux (reported to be not required for Ubuntu).  
                The commands within the batch files will work unchanged as long as Java has been installed correctly i.e. "java" 
                is in the PATH and it is the expected 1.5 or greater version.  You may need to do things like give executable 
                permissions to the batch files on Linux, e.g. "chmod +x *.bat".  And also unless you have "root" permissions, 
                you may have problems starting services on port 80 etc.
            </para>
            <para>
                JTrac by default will use a "data" directory that it will automatically create
                within the root (jtrac) folder.  The data directory will contain the files needed by HSQLDB
                (the embedded database) as well as hold uploaded attachments.  The "start.bat" file configures the 
                Jetty server to use port 80 which you can easily change by editing "start.bat".  You may need to do this 
                if for example JTrac does not start because a web-server (like Apache or IIS) is already running on port 80.
            </para>           
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="installation-settings">
            <title>Settings</title>
            <para>
                For e-mail notifications to work, an SMTP server needs to be configured in JTrac.
                Users who have the ADMIN role will be able to access the JTrac configuration settings
                screen from a link on the "OPTIONS" screen.  Note that you will need to provide values
                for the "mail.from" and the "jtrac.url.base" properties also, for things like the hyperlinks
                within e-mail to work properly.  JTrac also supports mail servers that require authentication
                or secure connections using SSL.  You can refer the descriptions of the available configuration 
                property settings available from the settings screen as shown below.             
            </para>
            <para>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject role="html">
                        <imagedata align="center" fileref="../images/settings.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>The JTrac settings screen where you can configure an e-mail / SMTP server</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </para>            
        </sect1>        
        <sect1 id="installation-war">
            <title>Using only the WAR file</title>
            <para>
                JTrac is designed so that you can be up and running by just deploying the WAR file into your 
                existing web-application server.  Note that you need a servlet 2.4 compliant container.  
                For example, if you have <ulink url="http://tomcat.apache.org/">Apache Tomcat</ulink> 5.5.X, 
                you can either copy the WAR file into the [tomcat.home]/webapps folder or choose to upload 
                the WAR file through the Tomcat console.
            </para>
            <para>                    
                JTrac saves database information and uploaded attachments into a directory on the server.
                This directory is logically called the "jtrac.home".  When you do a "quick-install" of JTrac
                by just deploying the WAR file, JTrac creates a ".jtrac" folder in the user home folder and
                uses that location as the home directory.
            </para>            
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="installation-custom">
            <title>Custom Installation</title>
            <para>                    
                To customize the location of "jtrac.home" you have the following three options.  On startup, JTrac tries to
                detect the value of "jtrac.home", and checks the following configuration options in the order listed below.
            </para>
            <sect2 id="installation-custom-initprops">
                <title>Edit the "jtrac-init.properties" file</title>
                <para>
                    If you explode (unzip) the WAR file, you can edit the /WEB-INF/classes/jtrac-init.properties file
                    and customize the location of "jtrac.home".  Note that you can choose to deploy JTrac as an exploded-war 
                    and it is not mandatory that you re-package (zip) the WAR file after editing "jtrac-init.properties".
                </para>
            </sect2>
            <sect2 id="installation-custom-servletparams">
                <title>Set a Servlet context parameter</title>
                <para>
                    For example you can specify the jtrac.home using the Tomcat administration console or as 
                    follows using a &lt;Context&gt; parameter.                     
                </para>
                <para>
                    <programlisting>
                        <![CDATA[                        
<Context docBase="${catalina.home}/jtrac/jtrac.war">
    <Parameter name="jtrac.home" value="C:/data/jtrac_home"/>
</Context>              ]]>
                    </programlisting>
                </para>                
            </sect2>            
            <sect2 id="installation-custom-systemparams">
                <title>Set a System / JVM parameter</title>            
                <para>
                    If you can easily set a system property called "jtrac.home" within the environment of your 
                    application server then you don't need to edit the WAR file.  Please look at the contents of "start.bat" 
                    to see an example of how the appropriate JVM (Java Virtual Machine) parameters can be set when deploying JTrac.  
                    For example, if you are using <ulink url="http://tomcat.apache.org/">Apache Tomcat</ulink> 5.5.X, you can 
                    set an environment variable called JAVA_OPTS before invoking the startup script (startup.bat / startup.sh).
                    Here is an example for Tomcat 5.5.X on Windows:                
                </para>
                <para>
                    <programlisting>

set JAVA_OPTS=-Djtrac.home=C:/data/jtrac_home -Dfile.encoding=UTF-8
                    </programlisting>
                </para>
                <para>
                    If "jtrac.home" has not been configured in any of the above ways, JTrac will create a folder called
                    ".jtrac" in the user home directory and proceed to use that as "jtrac.home".
                </para>
            </sect2>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="installation-database">
            <title>Using a different database such as MySQL</title>
            <para>                    
                You can configure the database that JTrac uses by editing the "jtrac.properties" file that JTrac expects
                within the "jtrac.home" folder.  Note that if JTrac does not find a "jtrac.properties" file in the
                expected location, JTrac creates a fresh one which is pre-configured for HSQLDB.  The contents of this file
                are as follows:                
            </para>
            <para>
                <programlisting>

database.driver=org.hsqldb.jdbcDriver
database.url=jdbc:hsqldb:file:${jtrac.home}/db/jtrac
database.username=sa
database.password=
hibernate.dialect=org.hibernate.dialect.HSQLDialect
hibernate.show_sql=false
                </programlisting>
            </para>          
            <para>
                You can change the database values and the hibernate dialect to match the settings of a 
                database that you have already.  When JTrac starts, it will connect to the database and
                create the schema if one does not already exist.
            </para>
            <para>
                If you edit the "jtrac.properties" file, ensure that there are no trailing spaces in the entries shown above
                (especially when cutting and pasting from somewhere).  This can save you a lot of frustration!
            </para>
            <para>
                Don't forget to make the database driver available for the web-application.  If you are using the bundled
                Jetty web-app server, this is as simple as copying the jar file into the "lib" folder along with the
                jetty jar files.  If you are using Tomcat, you can either place the jar file under "shared/lib" or within
                the "/WEB-INF/lib" folder of the "jtrac" (exploded) WAR itself.
            </para>            
            <para>
                Given below is a sample jtrac.properties file for MySQL.  Using the default "root" user is obviously
                not advisable from a security point of view and you should try and have a separate user for the database
                used by JTrac.
                <programlisting>

database.driver=com.mysql.jdbc.Driver
database.url=jdbc:mysql://localhost/jtrac
database.username=root
database.password=
hibernate.dialect=org.hibernate.dialect.MySQLDialect
hibernate.show_sql=false
                </programlisting>
            </para>
            <para>
                For MySQL, do not use the "autoReconnect=true" parameter in the MySQL URL, this is 
                <ulink url="http://dev.mysql.com/doc/connector/j/en/connector-j-usagenotes-j2ee.html#connector-j-usagenotes-tomcat">not recommended</ulink>
                by the MySQL team.  The <ulink url="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/dbcp/">Apache DBCP</ulink> 
                connection pool used internally by JTrac is configured to refresh stale database connections.                
            </para>
            <para>
                The default query to test idle database connections is "SELECT 1".  This has been reported
                to not work for databases such as Derby and Progress because they consider this invalid SQL.  You can
                customize the validation query by adding a "database.validationQuery" property in "jtrac.properties.
                If you set the validation query to an empty string, this effectively disables the periodic testing of
                idle database connections that Apache DBCP performs.
            </para>            
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="installation-windowsservice">
            <title>Installing as a Windows Service</title>
            <para>                    
                If you choose to use the bundled <ulink url="http://jetty.mortbay.org/">Jetty</ulink> web-application 
                server, you can easily install JTrac as a Windows service so that it can start automatically when 
                the host machine is switched on.  One of the big advantages of this is that the console window will be invisible 
                and will run in the background.  You can therefore avoid the possibility of the Jetty server getting
                terminated because somebody decided to close "that pesky DOS Window that gets in the way".  Having JTrac
                start automatically without requiring someone to log-in is ideal when you have a server that may be
                restarted occasionally due to power outages or maintenance.
            </para>
            <para>
                JTrac can be configured as a Windows service by using the 
                <ulink url="http://wrapper.tanukisoftware.org/">Java Service Wrapper</ulink> project.  For convenience, 
                the JTrac distribution contains a "wrapper.conf" file in the "etc" folder that is pre-configured for 
                the Java Service Wrapper.  But first you have to download the Java Service Wrapper distribution separately.
            </para>
            <para>
                Place some of the files from the Java Service Wrapper distribution into the JTrac folder structure
                as follows:
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>From the "bin" folder, copy "wrapper.exe" to the "jtrac" root folder</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>From the "lib" folder, copy "wrapper.jar" and "wrapper.dll" into the "jtrac/etc" folder</para>
                    </listitem>                               
                </itemizedlist>                 
            </para>
            <para>
                To install JTrac as a windows service, open a command prompt, change to the "jtrac" directory
                (where you extracted the JTrac distribution) and run the following command:
            </para>
            <para>
                <programlisting>

wrapper.exe -i etc/wrapper.conf
                </programlisting>
            </para>
            <para>
                This will install a windows service called "JTrac-Jetty".  You can now go to the Windows -
                Control Panel :: Administrative Tools :: Services dialog to start the "JTrac-Jetty" service.
                Note that this service is configured to automatically start when Windows starts, by default.
                To remove the service, you can use the following command:
            </para>
            <para>
                <programlisting>

wrapper.exe -r etc/wrapper.conf
                </programlisting>
            </para>
            <para>
                When running as a service under the Java Service Wrapper, you can look at the
                "wrapper.log" file in the "jtrac/logs" folder for troubleshooting.  Note that the 
                [jtrac.home] folder would contain the application log called "jtrac.log" as well.
            </para>
        </sect1>        
        <sect1 id="installation-upgrading">
            <title>Upgrading</title>
            <para>
                Please refer to the "<link linkend="upgrading">upgrading</link>" section of this document.
            </para>
        </sect1>
    </chapter>      
    
    <chapter id="faq">
        <title>FAQ</title>
        <sect1 id="faq-why">
            <title>Do we really need another issue tracker?</title>
            <para>
                There are indeed quite a few issue trackers available, both commercial and open source.
                JTrac has flexible workflow capabilities and offers a rare level of control over field-level 
                permissions. JTrac is designed to be able to handle requirements management in the future 
                and this an area where there is a clear lack of open source tools that support
                the needs of agile development teams.
            </para>
            <para>
                JTrac is also written from the ground up to make use of the very best and latest in Java.  For example
                JTrac is developed using JDK 5.0 features and is targeted at JSP 2.0 and above.
            </para>               
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="faq-architecture">
            <title>What is the JTrac architecture like?</title>
            <para>
                JTrac is built using the <ulink url="http://www.springframework.org">Spring Framework</ulink> as far as 
                possible and mostly uses 
                <ulink url="http://opensource.atlassian.com/confluence/spring/display/WEBFLOW/Home">Spring WebFlow</ulink>
                within the MVC layer apart from Spring MVC.  Also the <ulink url="http://www.acegisecurity.org/">Acegi Security</ulink>
                framework for Spring has been used.  JTrac is effectively a "light-weight" Java EE application and any 
                version 2.4 compliant servlet engine is sufficient for deployment.
            </para>
            <para>
                The presentation layer is JSP and JSTL based.  AJAX has been introduced only in a few screens where there 
                is a very clear need for it.  The <ulink url="http://prototype.conio.net/">Prototype</ulink> framework has been 
                used directly.
            </para>            
            <para>
                <ulink url="http://www.hibernate.org/">Hibernate</ulink> is used for data persistence.  This allows for 
                JTrac to be database neutral and any database supported by Hibernate can be used.
            </para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="faq-version">
            <title>Why start with version 2.0?  What about 1.0?</title>
            <para>
                There was an earlier version of JTrac which used to be hosted at <ulink url="https://jtrac.dev.java.net"/>
                That project was called "jTrac" (with a lowercase 'j') and it was based on Spring JDBC and MS Access.                
                JTrac has now been completely re-written to use Hibernate, Spring WebFlow and Acegi - and the 2.0 version
                number reflects this.
            </para>
        </sect1>     
    </chapter>    
    
    <chapter id="roadmap">
        <title>Roadmap</title>
        <para>
            Have a look at our detailed <link linkend="dev-guide">developer guide</link> and you will find that 
            JTrac has one of the most "developer-friendly" setups among open-source projects.  It will take you
            only a few minutes to be up and running no matter which java IDE you use.  We actively encourage 
            contributions and with your support JTrac can become better than it is today.
        </para>       
        <sect1 id="roadmap-hide">
            <title>Field-Level "Hide" Permissions</title>
            <para>
                In a future version of JTrac, the ability to even hide fields depending on the role and status
                will be implemented.  The design for this is already in place.
            </para>
        </sect1>       
        <sect1 id="roadmap-nested">
            <title>Nested Items</title>
            <para>
                JTrac will support "nested" items under a first-level "parent" item and the design
                and database schema for this is already in place.  This will allow users to split tasks into sub-tasks 
                and opens up other possibilities.  One of the plans in the roadmap is to build JTrac into a full-fledged
                requirements capture tool complete with test-case management and traceability.  JTrac can then be used to
                manage either XP (eXtreme Programming) or Use Case driven projects.
            </para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="roadmap-validation">
            <title>Custom Validation</title>
            <para>
                Using <ulink url="http://www.beanshell.org/">Beanshell</ulink>, users will be able to add custom validation 
                routines for item entry.  Even conditional validation across fields will be possible.
            </para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="roadmap-scheduler">
            <title>Custom Scheduled Jobs</title>
            <para>
                Again using Beanshell, users should be able to define routines to execute periodically, say at a pre-determined
                time every day.  This would allow triggers for events such as slippage of a "due-date" field.
                This can be combined with e-mail notifications.  Also a daily dashboard summary could be mailed out once
                the scheduler is in place.
            </para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="roadmap-email">
            <title>Submit By Email</title>
            <para>
                JTrac should be able to monitor an e-mail account and incoming e-mail should trigger
                creation / updation of items.  It would be handy to have attachments submitted through
                email also.
            </para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="roadmap-screenshot">
            <title>Screenshot Capture</title>
            <para>
                Using a Java applet, it should be possible for the user to upload a screenshot directly from the 
                system clipboard.  The user should be able to annotate (e.g. highlight a particular area of) the 
                image before uploading.
            </para>
        </sect1>        
        <sect1 id="roadmap-savedsearches">
            <title>Saved Searches</title>            
            <para>
                It should be possible for users to save search filters and re-use them.
            </para>
        </sect1>         
        <sect1 id="roadmap-wiki">
            <title>Wiki Engine</title>            
            <para>
                There is a plan to embed a wiki-engine into JTrac.  This will supplement the requirements management
                road map.
            </para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="roadmap-svn">
            <title>Subversion Integration</title>            
            <para>
                Integration with <ulink url="http://subversion.tigris.org/">Subversion</ulink> has already been implemented 
                using the <ulink url="http://tmate.org/svn/">JavaSVN</ulink> library and this will enable effective 
                integration of bug reports with commit history in the future. You can try out the existing experimental 
                support by going to the following url of your JTrac installation: http://[hostname]/jtrac/app/svn_form.htm                
            </para>
            <para>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject role="html">
                        <imagedata align="center" fileref="../images/svn-view.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <caption>
                        <para>Experimental Subversion support: commits per user report</para>
                    </caption>
                </mediaobject>
            </para>            
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="roadmap-tags">            
            <title>Tags</title>            
            <para>
                A one-to-many data model for being able to tag items "Web 2.0" style is already in place.  
                This would be ideal to track things such as mapping bugs to software release version numbers, 
                associating keywords with items and to do all kinds of other cool stuff.
            </para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="roadmap-feeds">            
            <title>RSS Feeds</title>            
            <para>
                RSS feeds will be introduced so that you can monitor new items and updates to items.
            </para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="roadmap-import">            
            <title>Import from other tools</title>            
            <para>
                Import from other issue tracking systems (such as BugZilla) to be considered.  The current version has
                an experimental Excel sheet import feature which you can access from the options screen if you are an
                admin user.  Once complete, this feature will allow you to import raw data from a spreadsheet, apply any
                data cleanup needed, identify and load custom fields / drop down values and finally import the items,
                creating a new Space and users if required.
            </para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="roadmap-sso">            
            <title>Single Sign On</title>            
            <para>
                Since JTrac uses the <ulink url="http://www.acegisecurity.org/">Acegi Security</ulink> 
                framework, it would be easy to configure it to use an existing 
                <ulink url="http://www.ja-sig.org/products/cas/">Central Authentication Service</ulink> (CAS) installation
                or LDAP server (even Windows Active Directory) for implementing Single Sign On. 
                In fact most of the configuration is in place and only needs to be documented.
            </para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="roadmap-xmlapi">            
            <title>XML API</title>            
            <para>
                JTrac should be able to expose a remote XML API (SOAP or REST) so that core functionality can be 
                invoked / integrated with other systems.
            </para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="roadmap-timetracking">            
            <title>Time Tracking</title>            
            <para>
                The database schema already has support for capturing planned vs actual effort against items.
                This needs to be implemented and obviously will open up a lot of possibilities.
            </para>
        </sect1>       
    </chapter>

    <chapter id="interim-builds">
        <title>Interim Builds</title>
        <sect1 id="interim-overview">
            <title>Overview</title>
            <para>
                For the convenience of those who would like to test the latest possible builds of JTrac without
                having to check-out and compile from version-control, binaries in WAR form are periodically uploaded
                to the JTrac web-site at this URL: <ulink url="http://j-trac.sourceforge.net/files/"/>
            </para>
            <para>
                You would be able to see the time-stamp of the last uploaded binary when you access the above URL.
                Subscribers to The JTrac mailing-list would be notified whenever a new binary is available.  This
                is not on a daily basis at the moment and happens only when significant changes or fixes are made in
                the development version.
            </para>
            <para>
                If you want to stay updated about the status of JTrac development as well as contribute and brainstorm 
                ideas for incorporation into future releases, please consider joining the JTrac mailing-list at:
                <ulink url="https://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/j-trac-users"/>
            </para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="interim-notes">
            <title>Notes on using Interim Builds</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Interim builds are provided only as WAR files.  If you are using the embedded Jetty
                            webapp-server, you have to replace the WAR that came along with the formal 
                            downloadable distribution.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            When you are replacing the WAR file in an existing installation it is best that you 
                            delete the contents of the webapp-server temporary / work folder before re-starting.  
                            Details on how to do this are provided in the "<link linkend="upgrading">upgrading</link>"
                            section of this document.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            In rare cases, there may be database schema changes.  This will be made clear in
                            the upload notification that is broadcast on the mailing-list.  If you wish to retain 
                            existing data, you will have to run a database upgrade script.  Details on how to do this are 
                            also provided in the "<link linkend="upgrading">upgrading</link>" section of this document.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Even if the database schema has changed, JTrac will re-create the database if one does
                            not exist on startup.  So when trying out the interim builds, this may be all that you really
                            want to do.  If you are using JTrac bundled with Jetty and / or with the embedded HSQLB database, 
                            removing the old database is as simple as deleting the "db" folder in which HSQLDB keeps
                            the data files.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>                                
                </itemizedlist>                     
            </para>
        </sect1>
    </chapter>
    
    <chapter id="upgrading">
        <title>Upgrading and Database Migration</title>
        <para>
            Upgrading to higher versions of JTrac is usually as simple as replacing the WAR file and deleting the web-app
            server temporary / work folder before re-starting.  In some rare cases the database schema may have changed and a
            script for updating the database would then be provided.  It may also happen that upgrading the Jetty version would be 
            recommended in case you happen to be using the bundled Jetty webapp-server for deploying JTrac.
        </para>
        <sect1 id="upgrading-war">
            <title>Deleting webapp temporary files</title>
            <para>
                In case you are using the bundled Jetty server in the JTrac distribution, you should delete the contents
                of the folder called "work".  Note that Jetty expects a folder called "work" to exist when it starts, 
                so ensure that you leave the empty "work" folder in place.
            </para>
            <para>
                If you are using another application server please follow the steps for removing temporary files
                corresponding to the server that you are using.
            </para>
        </sect1> 
        <sect1 id="upgrading-database">
            <title>Upgrading the Database</title>
            <para>
                If the JTrac release notes mention database schema changes, you need to additionally run an upgrade script
                before restarting the webapp-server with the new WAR in place.  Upgrade scripts come in the form of 
                <ulink url="http://www.beanshell.org/">Beanshell</ulink> scripts (*.bsh) and would be always released within
                the "etc" folder of the JTrac downloadable distribution.
            </para>
            <para>
                These files are tested on HSQLDB and may need minor changes to work with
                other databases.  No re-compilation is needed, therefore making it extremely easy for you to tweak them 
                if required.  Of course it is strongly recommended that you backup your old data before an upgrade.  
                Please use the <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/forum/forum.php?forum_id=552477">JTrac forums</ulink> 
                for help and for helping other users with your experiences.
            </para>
            <para>
                If you are shadowing the development builds you would be able to obtain the latest database upgrade
                scripts from here: <ulink url="http://svn.sourceforge.net/viewvc/j-trac/trunk/jtrac/etc/"/> Look for files 
                that end with ".bsh" - e.g: "jtrac-hsqldb-2_0rc3-to-2_0.bsh"
            </para>
            <para>
                Steps to follow:
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            First, stop the server, JTrac should not be connected to the database.
                        </para>                        
                    </listitem>                    
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            The "java" command should be available on the command line.
                        </para>                        
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Get the latest beanshell jar file (~300 KB) from here: <ulink url="http://www.beanshell.org/bsh-2.0b4.jar"/>
                        </para>                        
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Get the right JDBC driver for your database. If you have been using the embedded HSQLDB 
                            database, hsqldb-x-x-x.jar will be available in the jtrac war file within "lib".
                        </para>                        
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Edit the connection params (jdbc URL, username, password) to match your database. For HSQLDB, 
                            to make it easier - you can copy the beanshell jar and the hsqldb jar into the "db" folder of 
                            "jtrac.home".  The db folder will contain a "jtrac.script" file. There may also be a "jtrac.log" 
                            file. So when you are in the same directory as the HSQLDB data files, the URL is 
                            "jdbc:hsqldb:file:jtrac". Otherwise, replace the "jtrac" part in the URL with the relative or 
                            absolute path of where the "jtrac.script" file exists on your file-system.
                        </para>                        
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Execute the beanshell script from the command line.  The database driver should be added to the
                            classpath along with the beanshell jar.  This is how the command would look like:
                <programlisting>

java -cp bsh-2.0b4.jar;hsqldb-1.8.0.1.jar bsh.Interpreter jtrac-hsqldb-2_0rc3-to-2_0.bsh
                </programlisting>                                                                            
                        </para>                            
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            If there were no errors, you can now upgrade the WAR (don't forget to delete the temporary files) 
                            and restart.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="upgrading-jetty">
            <title>Upgrading Jetty</title>
            <para>
                If you are using the embedded Jetty web-app server, you can also choose to upgrade the JAR files that 
                make up Jetty.  This is optional, but is as simple as overwriting the contents of the "lib" directory 
                with the corresponding files within the new distribution.  You can easily check if the Jetty related JAR 
                file versions have changed because the file-names clearly include the version numbers.
            </para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="upgrading-migrating">
            <title>Database Migration</title>
            <para>
                Using the Beanshell based approach above, it is relatively straightforward to port data into another
                database.  This is useful especially in those cases where you start off using JTrac with the embedded
                HSQLDB database and then decide to scale up and move to something like MySQL.
            </para>
            <para>
                First, you should start the application re-configured to point to the new database and let JTrac
                do the hard work of creating all the database tables.  It is not necessary for Jtrac to be shut-down
                before proceeding with the next step,  but don't log-in yet!
            </para>
            <para>
                A Beanshell script called "jtrac-hsqldb-to-mysql.bsh" is available in the "etc" folder of the
                JTrac distribution.  You can execute this just like described in the previous section on upgrading.
                Note that you will need to have both the database drivers on the classpath in this case.  You should
                of course edit the database connection parameters (for database 1 and database 2) to suit your environment.
            </para>
            <para>
                This particular script is extremely generic and it should be possible to use this to migrate across
                combinations of databases other than HSQLDB and MySQL.
            </para>
        </sect1>         
    </chapter>
    
    <chapter id="dev-guide">
        <title>Developer Guide</title>
        <sect1 id="dev-prerequisites">
            <title>Pre Requisites</title>
            <para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>JDK 5.0</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><ulink url="http://maven.apache.org/">Maven 2.0</ulink></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Your Favourite IDE (e.g. NetBeans)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Access to the internet (or a Maven 2 repository)</para>
                    </listitem>                                
                </itemizedlist> 
            </para>
            <para>
                The JTrac development environment uses Maven 2 only for dependency management and generating and deploying the JTrac 
                website hosted at SourceForge.  Almost all other development actions (clean, compile etc) are fired through
                a detailed Ant script that is able to use the dependency information managed by Maven.  Using Maven ensures that
                no binaries (JAR files) need to be checked into version control at all.
            </para>
            <para>
                You can get some idea about the details and rationale of the custom Ant + Maven integration approach from
                <ulink url="http://ptrthomas.wordpress.com/2006/04/18/another-way-to-integrate-maven-2-with-ant-and-netbeans/">this blog post.</ulink>
            </para>
            <para>
                Although NetBeans is preferred by the JTrac developers, depending on an "IDE Neutral" Ant script
                ensures that you would easily be able to use Eclipse (or any other IDE of your choice) without any problems.
            </para>
            <para>
                If you get stuck or have any questions about setting up and getting started, feel free to use the 
                <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/forum/forum.php?forum_id=552477">JTrac forums</ulink> for help.
            </para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="dev-check-prerequisites">
            <title>Check Prerequisites</title>
            <para>
                Maven 2 should be in your "PATH".  You can test this out by opening a command prompt and trying to run the
                command "mvn".  If this is set, you are ready to move to the next step.
            </para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="dev-download">
            <title>Download / Extract Source</title>
            <para>
                Download the source code from 
                <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=162983&amp;package_id=184104">SourceForge</ulink>
                and extract it to a convenient location.  You will end up with two directories ("antprops" and "jtrac").
            </para>
            <para>
                You could choose to check out the source code directly from the JTrac SourceForge Subversion repository.
                You have to perform two separate check-outs, one for the "antprops" Maven plugin and of course "jtrac" itself.
            </para> 
           <para>
               Subversion URL for the Maven 2 "Antprops" plugin:
                <programlisting>

https://svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/j-trac/trunk/maven-antprops-plugin
                </programlisting>               
           </para>
           <para>
               Subversion URL for the JTrac source code:
                <programlisting>

https://svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/j-trac/trunk/jtrac
                </programlisting>               
           </para>
           <para>
               If you are behind a corporate firewall that requires NTLM authentication, you can try a tool called
               <ulink url="http://ntlmaps.sourceforge.net/">NTLMAPS</ulink> to check out from Subversion.
           </para>
           <para>
               If you are using Windows, we recommend <ulink url="http://tortoisesvn.tigris.org/">TortoiseSVN</ulink>
                as a Subversion client.
           </para>           
        </sect1>        
        <sect1 id="dev-antprops-install">
            <title>Install the "Antprops" Maven 2 Plugin</title>
            <para>
                This is a "one-time" step that installs a custom Maven 2 plugin into your local repository.
                Open a command prompt and change to the (root of the) "antprops" directory.  Run the following command:                
            </para>
            <para>
                <programlisting>

mvn install
                </programlisting>
            </para>
            <para>
                If this does not work, maybe you are not connected to the internet.  Here's a tip that may help if you 
                are behind an HTTP proxy.  This has been reported to work even when the proxy requires NTLM authentication.  
                You can append a parameter when running Maven commands as follows:
            </para>
            <para>
                <programlisting>

mvn install -Dhttp.proxyHost=172.19.56.56
                </programlisting>
            </para>
            <para>
                Note that if your proxy port is different from the default 80, you will have to add an "http.proxyPort" 
                parameter as well.
            </para>             
        </sect1> 
        <sect1 id="dev-build-properties">
            <title>Customize Ant Build Properties File</title>
            <para>
                The downloaded source code should contain a sample "build.properties" file or you can look at the XML comment
                provided at the top of "build.xml" for the structure.  Actually both entries are optional and you will require 
                them only if you want to use Tomcat (instead of Jetty) and also try the <ulink url="http://watij.com/">Watij</ulink>
                automated functional test script.
            </para>
            <para>
                If you are in a hurry and can't wait to start working on JTrac you can skip setting up Tomcat or Watij.  
                But then, ensure that you remove the build.properties file if one already exists - before the next step.
            </para>            
        </sect1>        
        <sect1 id="dev-antprops-generate">
            <title>Generate Dependencies Properties File</title>
            <para>
                Open a command prompt and change to the "jtrac" folder.  Run the following command:                
            </para>
            <para>
                <programlisting>

mvn antprops:generate
                </programlisting>
            </para>
            <para>
                This step will not only download all the required JAR files (which may take time only for the first time),
                but also generate a standard properties file that will contain all the information required for
                the Ant build script to operate.  The file generated is called "build-deps.properties"
            </para>
            <para>
                Note that you need to perform this step every time the "pom.xml" file changes.  This happens rarely 
                and typically when newer versions of JTrac dependencies (e.g. Spring and Hibernate) are available.  Keep
                watching for changes in the versions of JTrac dependencies or specifically changes to "pom.xml" to avoid 
                any problems.
            </para>          
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="dev-eclipse">
            <title>Import project into your IDE</title>
            <para>
                If you are a NetBeans user you are ready to build and run JTrac!  Just use the "Open Project"
                option from the "File" menu, browse to and select the "jtrac" folder.  You should be able to open it 
                as a valid NetBeans project.
            </para>
            <para>
                If you want to use Eclipse, that's easy as well.  First you have to run the following command and
                Maven will then generate the Eclipse project descriptor files for you.
            </para>
            <para>
                <programlisting>

mvn eclipse:eclipse
                </programlisting>
            </para>
            <para>
                That should create the ".project" and the ".classpath" files.  Now its just a matter of
                importing "Existing Project into Workspace" within Eclipse.  Note that the Eclipse project descriptor
                files also need to be re-generated when JTrac dependencies change, i.e. when "pom.xml" changes.
                Make sure you do this also if you ever run "mvn antprops:generate".
            </para>
            <para>
                For Eclipse to work with Maven 2, you have to have a classpath variable called "M2_REPO" set correctly.
                Refer the <ulink url="http://maven.apache.org/guides/mini/guide-ide-eclipse.html">Maven 2 documentation</ulink>
                for details on how to do this.
            </para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="dev-building">
            <title>Building And Running JTrac</title>
            <para>
                You can explore all the Ant targets that are available. You can also try the "jetty-start" 
                Ant target straight away that will compile, create and deploy the WAR as well as boot a Jetty server.
                For NetBeans users, the "jetty-start" target is neatly mapped to the "Run Main Project (F6)" shortcut, 
                once you make JTrac the "main project".  Note that this Ant target is smart enough to detect if Jetty 
                is already running and will perform a shutdown if required before re-starting.
            </para>
            <para>
                Maven has been configured to download the Jetty web server which drastically reduces the amount of
                setup that you need to do in order to set up your development environment.  Since JTrac creates 
                the HSQLDB database if required on startup, you do not need to worry about  installing, configuring 
                and creating any database either.
            </para>            
            <para>
                Note that if you use NetBeans, you can debug and set breakpoints even in JSPs.  If you are interested
                in more information as to why you should consider using NetBeans for development, please refer this
                <ulink url="http://ptrthomas.wordpress.com/2006/04/11/reasons-for-switching-to-netbeans/">blog post.</ulink>
            </para>
            <para>
                If you want to use Apache Tomcat instead of Jetty, just have "build.properties" point to a valid Tomcat instance.            
                By now, you may have noticed that because of the 
                <ulink url="http://ptrthomas.wordpress.com/2006/03/25/how-to-start-and-stop-tomcat-from-ant/">Ant script</ulink>, 
                you don't even need a Tomcat or Jetty plugin in either NetBeans or Eclipse.
            </para>            
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="dev-translating">
            <title>Adding a language translation for JTrac</title>
            <para>
                JTrac has multi-language support and you can easily add a new language without re-compiling JTrac.
                All you need to do is introduce a translated version of the existing "messages.properties" file into
                the "/WEB-INF/classes" folder.  Note that you will need to unzip the WAR file in order to add more files to it.
            </para>
            <para>
                For example, if you need to add a translation into French, a file called "messages_fr.properties" should exist.
                You can refer the list of Java locale codes 
                <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/guide/intl/locale.doc.html">here</ulink>.  Note that country
                specific locales are also supported, for example "fr_CA" means "French, Canada".  
            </para>
            <para>
                You can look at the existing translations e.g. "messages_de.properties" as examples. Note that
                JTrac needs to be restarted for changes to the properties files to take effect.  However,
                switching the language for any user can easily be done anytime from the "Edit Your Profile" link on the
                options screen and this takes effect the instant the user saves his profile.
            </para>
            <para>
                You can also get the latest versions of the "messages.properties" as well as the available
                translations directly from version control at this url:
                <ulink url="http://svn.sourceforge.net/viewvc/j-trac/trunk/jtrac/src/main/resources/"/>
                Since these may change a lot, it is recommended that you check here as well before submitting
                a translation.
            </para>
            <para>                
                You can use this nice open-source tool called <ulink url="https://prbeditor.dev.java.net/">PRBEditor</ulink>
                that really helps by showing the English and translated versions side by side on a single screen.  It also
                takes care of handling special characters.
            </para>
        </sect1>
    </chapter>
    
</book>
